// Initialize the display.
$('rules-section').show();
$('#quiz-section').css('visibility', 'hidden');
$('#result').text('');

// Listen and respond
window.onload = function () {

    $('#start').click(function () {

        startGame();

    });

    $('#quiz-form input').on('change', function () {

        var value = $('input[name=opt]:checked', '#quiz-form').val();

        timer.stop();

        clearTimeout(timeoutId);
        timeoutId = setTimeout(function () {

            checkAnswer(value);

        }, 1000);
    });
};

// Data

var quizArr = [{
        question: '"Intelligence plus characterâ€”that is the goal of true education."',
        option1: 'Maya Angelou',
        option2: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.',
        option3: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        answer: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'
    },
    {
        question: '"If you are always trying to be normal you will never know how amazing you can be."',
        option1: 'Maya Angelou',
        option2: 'Nelson Mandela',
        option3: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        answer: 'Maya Angelou'
    },
    {
        question: '"Be the change that you wish to see in the world."',
        option1: 'Maya Angelou',
        option2: 'Mother Teresa',
        option3: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        answer: 'Mahatma Gandhi'
    },
    {
        question: '"If you want to change the world, go home and love your family."',
        option1: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        option2: 'Mother Teresa',
        option3: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.',
        answer: 'Mother Teresa'
    },
    {
        question: '"Do not learn how to react learn how to respond."',
        option1: 'Buddha',
        option2: 'Confucius',
        option3: 'Aristotle',
        answer: 'Buddha'
    },
    {
        question: '"True peace is not merely the absence of tension; it is the presence of justice."',
        option1: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.',
        option2: 'Malcolm X',
        option3: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        answer: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'
    },
    {
        question: '"Obstacles are those frightful things you see when you take your eyes off the goal."',
        option1: 'Steve Jobs',
        option2: 'Albert Einstein',
        option3: 'Henry Ford',
        answer: 'Henry Ford'
    },
    {
        question: '"It always seems impossible until it\'s done."',
        option1: 'Nelson Mandela',
        option2: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.',
        option3: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        answer: 'Nelson Mandela'
    },
    {
        question: '"Resentment is like drinking poison and then hoping it will kill your enemies."',
        option1: 'Mahatma Gandhi',
        option2: 'Nelson Mandela',
        option3: 'Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.',
        answer: 'Nelson Mandela'
    },
    {
        question: '"Only two things are infinite, the universe and human stupidity, and I\'m not sure about the former."',
        option1: 'Winston Churchill',
        option2: 'Albert Einstein',
        option3: 'Isaac Newton',
        answer: 'Albert Einstein'
    }

];

//----- variables -----//

var totalSeconds = 30; // number of seconds per question
var intervalId; // timer second intervals
var timeoutId; // coordinates questions with timer
var clockRunning = false; // determines whether to clear interval
var quizIndex = 0; // input array
var numAsked = 0; // number of questions asked
var numCorrect = 0; // number of correct answers

var timer = {

    time: totalSeconds,

    // start countdown

    start: function () {

        // reset the timer

        var seconds = totalSeconds;
        timer.time = seconds;

        // display seconds
        $('#clock').text('00:' + seconds);

        // start countdown

        if (!clockRunning) {

            // count() is the timer's workhorse

            intervalId = setInterval(timer.count, 1000);
            clockRunning = true;
        }
    },

    // stop game & show answers

    stop: function () {

        clockRunning = false;
        clearInterval(intervalId);
    },

    // countdown

    count: function () {

        timer.time--;
        var t = timer.time;

        if (t < 1) {

            // time's up

            $('#clock').text('00:00');
            timer.stop();

            timeoutId = setTimeout(function () {

                checkAnswer('-1');

            }, 1000);

        } else if (t < 10) {

            // single digit

            $('#clock').text('00:0' + t);

        } else {

            $('#clock').text('00:' + t);

        }
    },
};

function startGame() {

    // switch display to rules 
    $('#rules-section').hide();
    $('#quiz-section').css('visibility', 'visible');
    $('#quiz-form').css('visibility', 'visible');

    // start volley between questions and answers
    getQuestion();
}

function getQuestion() {

    var i = quizIndex;

    if (i === quizArr.length) { // no more questions

        endGame();

    } else {

        // set timer
        timer.start();

        timeoutID = setTimeout(function () {
            return;
        }, totalSeconds * 3000);

        // reset state

        $('.option').attr('disabled', false);
        $('.option').prop('checked', false);

        // load form

        $('#question').text(quizArr[i].question);
        $('#label-1').text(quizArr[i].option1);
        $('#label-2').text(quizArr[i].option2);
        $('#label-3').text(quizArr[i].option3);
        $('#answer').text('');
    }
}

function checkAnswer(value) {

    var choice;
    var answer = quizArr[quizIndex].answer;

    numAsked++;

    $('.option').attr('disabled', true);

    // get label text by button value
    switch (value) {

        case ('1'):
            {
                choice = $('#label-1').text();
                break;
            }
        case ('2'):
            {

                choice = $('#label-2').text();
                break;
            }
        case ('3'):
            {

                choice = $('#label-3').text();
                break;
            }
        case ('-1'):
            {
                choice = '-1';
            }
    }

    if (choice === answer) {

        numCorrect++;
        $('#answer').text('Yes! The correct answer is ' + answer + '.');

    } else if (choice === '-1') {

        $('#answer').text('Too slow! The correct answer is ' + answer + '.');

    } else {

        $('#answer').text('Nope! The correct answer is ' + answer + '.');
    }

    // prepare for next question

    quizIndex++;

    timeoutId = setTimeout(function () {

        getQuestion();

    }, 3000);

}

function endGame() {

    timer.stop();

    // display results

    $('#quiz-form').css('visibility', 'hidden');
    $('#answer').text('');
    $('#result').text('Congratulations! You got ' + numCorrect + ' answers right out of ' + numAsked + ' questions.');

    timeoutId = setTimeout(function () {

        resetGame();

    }, 3000);
}

function resetGame() {

    quizIndex = 0;
    $('#rules-section').show();
    $('#answer').text('');
    $('#result').text('');
    $('#quiz-section').css('visibility', 'hidden');
}